Today's דף daf is כף kaf but we started at the bottom
of כ' עמוד א' Chaf Amud Aleph about five lines from the
bottom and we're dealing with מוציא שם רע. Motzi Shem Ra. We
just saw the ירושלמי Yerushalmi that gave two explanations of this debate.
Are they debating when the case is against a woman? Starts with
ממונית קביעה mamonit k'veivah to דיני נפשות. dinei nefashot. Or the case
is against the man where it starts with both דיני נפשות dinei
nefashot and דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, דיני נפשות dinei nefashot against the
עדים edim and דיני ממונות dinei mamonot against the man. So that's
two ways the ירושלמי Yerushalmi explain it. Nice clear way of framing
it. Let's see what the בבלי Bavli says. וחכמים אומרים מוציא שם
רע בעשרים ושלושה. V'Chachamim omrim motzi shem ra b'esrim u'shlosha. The case
of מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra the חכמים Chachamim say is
twenty-three and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's three. The גמרא Gemara
says וכי יש בו v'chi yesh bo כ' עמוד א' Chaf Amud
Aleph in the בבלי Bavli five lines from the bottom. וכי יש
בו דיני נפשות מאי הוי? V'chi yesh bo dinei nefashot mai havei?
Right? So because the חכמים Chachamim said back it's twenty-three because there's
an element of דיני נפשות dinei nefashot in it. So it says
so what if there's an element of דיני נפשות dinei nefashot in
it? We're dealing with the דיני ממונות dinei mamonot aspect of it.
אמר עולא חוששין ללעז מפלגי. Amar Ulla chosheshin l'la'az miflagi. The debate
is are you afraid of rumor or like a bad you know
gossip? רבי מאיר סבר אין חוששין ללעז. Rabbi Meir savar ein chosheshin
l'la'az. You're not afraid of rumor. ורבנן סברי חוששין ללעז. V'rabbanan savri
chosheshin l'la'az. You're afraid of rumor. So what the heck does that
mean? So here for once the בבלי Bavli is a lot more
cryptic than the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. I'll tell you what רש"י Rashi says
and then I'll tell you what תוספות Tosafot says. רש"י Rashi says
what it means is it's a case against the woman. You start
with three. That's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. But the חכמים Chachamim
say oh but once people start hearing, oh did you hear? There's
a case against this woman. She wasn't a virgin on her wedding
night. What? What's that about? Or whatever. People might realize with that
might lead to witnesses coming forward and actually testifying that she committed
adultery. Not that she wasn't a virgin. And then it could turn
into the capital case, not just she wasn't a virgin. And then
it could turn into the
capital crime and then it would require twenty-three. So רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says you know no no no we're not afraid of that.
It's a ממונות mamonot case you start with three. And the חכמים
Chachamim say it could turn into a דיני נפשות dinei nefashot case,
that's חוששין ללעז chosheshin l'la'az and therefore it is
twenty-three. So that's a funny phrase about חוששין ללעז chosheshin l'la'az because
it's not a לעז la'az I guess because of gossiping about her
but it's really a question about getting the word out and bringing
witnesses. Okay but then it's a simple framing of is it starts
with דיני ממונות dinei mamonot against the woman and are we concerned
that it would evolve into a דיני נפשות dinei nefashot case. That's
the way רש"י Rashi says it. תוספות Tosafot does not like this
at all. First of all he says that's not what the word
לעז la'az means. Secondly תוספות Tosafot says that the phrase of מוציא
שם רע motzi shem ra always refers to the case against the
man, not the case against the woman. Does that sound like something?
Where did we just hear that? In the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. The ירושלמי
Yerushalmi started with an opinion that it was a case against the
woman and then the pushback in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi was what are
you talking about? מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra means a case
against the man. It doesn't mean a case against the woman. So
תוספות Tosafot has a lot a lot of questions on רש"י. Rashi.
And therefore
תוספות Tosafot says no no no. We are not talking about the
case against the woman. We're talking about the cases against the man.
Okay. And therefore רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says three because he pays
ממון. mamon. So what's the חכמים' Chachamim חוששין ללעז chosheshin l'la'az type
of a concern? So the חוששין ללעז chosheshin l'la'az type of a
concern תוספות Tosafot he does a lot of like what do you
call it? Summersaults in order to explain this. He תוספות Tosafot wants
to suggest, and I don't want to get into this it's complicated,
I'll just tell you very quickly that there could be a case
against the man without the עדים edim being חייב מיתה. chayav misa.
How could there be a case against a man without the עדים
edim חייב מיתה? chayav misa? We always assume only when the עדים
edim are proven זוממים zomemim is the man does the man have
to pay and get the lashes. So תוספות Tosafot says, and this
is a huge חידוש chidush which תוספות Tosafot acknowledges eventually, which is
that let's say the man brought witnesses that the woman committed adultery
and then other witnesses came and they didn't make them זוממים zomemim
but they contradicted them. They gave opposite testimony. No no no the
woman was with us. You couldn't have been. The guy you claim
she committed adultery with we saw him somewhere else. It's not זוממים.
zomemim. You're not saying the witnesses were somewhere else. It neutralizes the
witnesses. So תוספות Tosafot is making a claim that
even in the case where they were neutralized, the husband would have
to pay the fine and get lashes which is a huge חידוש
chidush because you don't know the husband is lying in that case
right? It's just two against two. But that's how תוספות Tosafot tries
to make it parallel to this issue of the woman. It starts
with a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot against the man okay because his
witnesses were neutralized but it could turn into a דיני נפשות dinei
nefashot case because the witnesses could become זוממים. zomemim. All right so
it's very very complicated and that חוששין ללעז chosheshin l'la'az would be,
by the way the לעז la'az for the תוספות Tosafot is and
this answers Michael's point is and this you could say even according
to רש"י Rashi as well. The לעז la'az is not the rumor
will get out and you'll have to and you know and will
turn into a דיני נפשות dinei nefashot case. That would be a
good thing. The לעז la'az will be when we have to add
will that make the original judges look bad? Okay because people... Say,
"Oh, why'd you have to add? Must be they weren't competent." Okay,
so חוששים ללעז chosheshim la-la'az means, well okay, maybe we'll turn into
a דיני נפשות dinei nefashos case. Let's worry about it then. Why
not find out? When that happens, we'll just add judges. No, no,
no. The answer is we don't want to do that cause חוששים
ללעז. chosheshim la-la'az. It'll look bad to the original judges. And the
other approach will say אין חוששים ללעז. ein chosheshim la-la'az. You know
what? If we have to add, we'll add. We'll worry about it
then. We don't care how it might make the original judges look
like. Okay, so I know that was all very complicated, but what
I wanted you to hear was that תוספות Tosfos takes this גמרא...
Gemara... first of all, there's a question: what does חוששים ללעז chosheshim
la-la'az mean? Does חוששים ללעז chosheshim la-la'az mean we're afraid that the
word, the word will get out and it'll turn into a דיני
נפשות dinei nefashos case? Or does חוששים ללעז chosheshim la-la'az mean,
okay, it'll turn into a דיני נפשות dinei nefashos case, but do
we have to worry that adding judges will make the original judges
look bad? That's, you know, whatever. Those are two meanings of חוששים
ללעז. chosheshim la-la'az. What they both share is that the question is
that the דיני ממונות dinei mamonos case will turn into a דיני
נפשות dinei nefashos case. Okay, and that's the question. And therefore do
we have to start with twenty-three because that might happen? But the
other point is that תוספות Tosfos tries to turn this into the
case against the man, which is exactly the second opinion in the
ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. So I want you to just look at one line.
If you turn the page, ח' עמוד ב', ches amud beis, at
the bottom of this
תוספות, Tosfos, והביא האב עדים והזימום, ve-heivi ha-av edim ve-hizimum, תוספות Tosfos
says, so after he's trying to work out the whole סוגיא sugya
according to him and according to רש"י, Rashi, at the end he
says the following. He says,
ובירושלמי, u-vi'Yerushalmi, you see three lines before חוששים, chosheshim, three lines before
the end of that תוספות, Tosfos, והביא האב, ve-heivi ha-av, on ח'
עמוד ב',
ches amud
beis, 8b, he says, ובירושלמי מצא רשב"א, u-vi'Yerushalmi matza Rashba, that's not
the רשב"א Rashba that we know from the Sefardi world, that's a...
this is רבי שמשון, Rebbi Shimshon, ר"ש, Rash, מצא רשב"א פלוגתא
דאמוראי.
matza Rashba
plugta d'Amorai. איכא דמפרש פלוגתא
לענין כתובה כדמפרש בקונטרס ואיכא דמפרש לענין קוסלאי סלע
כדמפרש רבינו תם. ika de-mefaresh plugta l'inyan kesuvah k'de-mefaresh be-kuntres v'ika de-mefaresh
l'inyan kusla'ei sela k'de-mefaresh Rabbeinu Tam. Look at that. So the two
opinions in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, the בבלי Bavli is cryptic. Is it
about him or is it about her? And those are the major
debate of the ראשונים, Rishonim, how to read the בבלי. Bavli. And
then תוספות Tosfos says, guess what? This debate of the ראשונים Rishonim
actually was the same thing that's being debated in the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi.
Because what it's pointing to is the inherent ambiguity in the סוגיא
sugya itself. And often you find this, right? That debates of
ראשונים Rishonim parallel, you know, like implicit different reads of the text,
right? And those implicit different reads might be reflected in like a
בבלי ירושלמי Bavli-Yerushalmi difference, and here actually two opinions that are explicitly
identified. So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi actually has a very clear framing of
this. In our גמרא Gemara it's less clear. But let's go back
to our גמרא. Gemara. We're going to work with רש"י Rashi just
because he's easier, okay? And actually that was the first approach of
the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. So let's go back.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר עולא, amar Ulla, let's pick it
up again, four lines from the bottom, אמר עולא בחוששים ללעז קמיפלגי.
amar Ulla be-chosheshim la-la'az kamipalgi. רבי מאיר סבר אין חוששים ללעז. Rebbi
Meir savar ein chosheshim la-la'az. So you start with a בית דין
beis din of three because it's against the woman. We're going to
read it that way. And רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says, "I'm not
afraid that that will turn into twenty-three." Okay, and if it does
turn into twenty-three, you can just add judges, and I'm not afraid
it'll make the earlier judges look bad. ורבנן סברי חוששים ללעז. ve-rabbanan
savri chosheshim la-la'az. No, we are afraid it'll turn into twenty-three, and
we don't want to add the judges then, it'll make the original
judges look bad. So we're going to start with twenty-three right now.
That's what עולא Ulla says. רבא אמר... Rava amar... what? Okay, רבא
אמר, Rava amar, I gave you both readings of the word לעז.
la'az. רבא אמר כולי עלמא ללעז לא חיישינן. Rava amar kuli alma
la-la'az lo chashinan. Everybody agrees we're not afraid of a three turning
into a case of a twenty-three. Okay? והכא בחוששים לכבודן
של ראשונים קמיפלגי. ve-hacha be-chosheshim lichvodan shel rishonim kamipalgi. The debate is,
are you concerned about the honor of the first group of the
first judges? And that sounds like חוששים ללעז, chosheshim la-la'az, but no,
no, no. He's going to explain it the following way. והכא במאי
עסקינן כגון דאיכניף בי עשרים ותלתא. ve-hacha be-mai askinan k'gon d'ichneif bei
esrim v'sasla. It's the opposite. It's not that you're going to add
judges but that you're going to take away judges. So it's like
לעז, la'az, but it's almost like, you know, a different variation of
it. Okay? You started with a בית דין beis din of twenty-three.
The guy said, "I have witnesses that my wife committed adultery," and
he got together a court of
twenty-three. Okay? למידן דיני נפשות. lemidan dinei nefashos. ואיבדר, v'ibdar, they scattered.
He said, "Ugh, you know, the בית דין," beis din, meaning the
בית דין beis din broke up because it was clear like he
wasn't going to be able to prove that his wife committed adultery.
Okay? ואמר להו דיינו לי מיהא דיני ממונות. ve-amar lehu dayinu li
miha dinei mamonos. Where, where are you? Don't all go running away!
Fine, I can't prove she committed adultery, but let me just make
a proof that she, she deserves to lose her כתובה. kesuvah. Okay,
and therefore the debate is, it's like the opposite from three to
twenty-three, it's from twenty-three to three. So רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says
you let twenty of them go home, okay, take care of their...
go to their wives and kids, and three stay along around to
do דיני ממונות. dinei mamonos. וחכמים ve-chachamim say since we started with
twenty-three, we're going to keep the twenty-three. It would not be, it
would be a concern of the honor of the judges if you
sort of dismiss twenty of them. Why? I don't know. Okay, I
like עולא's Ulla's read better than רבא's. Rava's. Anyway, מיתיבי, meisivei, the
גמרא Gemara asks you, we have a ברייתא beraisa that says the
following:
וחכמים אומרים, ve-chachamim omrim, תבעו ממון... tav'u mamon... בשלושה טיבו נפשות בעשרים
ושלושה. beshlosha tavo nefashot beesrim ushlosha. Now this sounds like a רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir position, but חכמים Chachamim say look, we'll agree to
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that if it was only a דיני ממונות
dinei mamonot case it would be three. But if it was basically
a דיני נפשות dinei nefashot case, it was a capital crime, it
would be 23. So okay, but that sounds exactly like what רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir said. So what does that mean? So בשלמא bishlama
לרבה le'Rabbah או לרבא, le'Rava, there's a question whether it was רבה
Rabbah or רבא, Rava, we get: טיבו ממונא תחילה, tavo mamona techila,
if the whole case began with a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot case
then everybody agrees בשלושה. bishlosha. טיבו נפשות תחילה, tavo nefashot techila, if
it began with a capital case but then it turned out that
he couldn't produce the witnesses and you were left with three and
it was left with a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot case, then טיבו
נפשות תחילה אפילו ממונא, tavo nefashot techila afilu mamona, then even if
you're left with a monetary case, בעשרים ושלושה be'esrim ushlosha you keep
it as 23. That works very nicely, because there חכמים Chachamim are
saying if you started with a monetary case we agree to you.
But if it started with a capital case you're going to leave
it at 23. אלא לעולא קשיא, ela le'Ulla kashya, but for עולא
Ulla it's difficult because עולא Ulla says the case is you started
with a monetary case. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says three and the
חכמים Chachamim say 23 because they're afraid that the monetary is going
to turn into a דיני נפשות dinei nefashot case. So how do
you read here that the חכמים Chachamim seeming to agree to רבי
מאיר? Rabbi Meir? So אמר רבא, amar Rava, so רבא Rava said,
אני וארי שבחבורה, ani ve'ari she'bachabura, me and the lion in our
group. Who's the lion? תרגימנא, targimna, we've explained this ברייתא braita to
be consistent with עולא. Ulla. ומנו, u'mano, who is this lion? רבי
חייא בר אבין. Rabbi Chiya bar Avin. Okay, now here's how we're
going to explain this ברייתא braita to work for עולא, Ulla, because
עולא Ulla seems to say that when you start with a ממונות
mamonot case, that's the debate, 3 or 23. So why are the
rabbis agreeing when you start with ממונות mamonot it's three? So הכא
במאי עסקינן, hacha be'mai askinan, what are we talking about? שהביא הבעל
עדים שזינתה
והביא האב עדים והזימום. she'hevi habaal edim she'zinta ve'hevi ha'av edim ve'hizimum.
Okay, so the husband brought witnesses that she committed adultery and
the father brought witnesses to prove that they were זוממין, zomemin, meaning
what we're now doing is we're flipping it from the case against
the woman to the case against the man. His witnesses are proven
to be עדים זוממין edim zomemin והזימום לעדי הבעל. ve'hizimum le'adei habaal.
So now when we're dealing with the case against the man,
לגבות ממון מבעל בשלושה, ligbot mamon mibaal bishlosha, when we're coming to
go ahead and have the case against
the man, excuse me, and get the money, that's three. Okay, because
the man can never turn into a דיני נפשות dinei nefashot case,
meaning the witnesses will get killed, but the man is always going
to remain a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot case. So in this case,
when you're coming to have the case against the man, it's going
to, we'll admit it's three. ובמקום נפשות בעשרים ושלושה, u'bimkom nefashot be'esrim
ushlosha, but in a case of דיני נפשות dinei nefashot 23. What
does that mean? Presumably maybe it means the עדים edim are 23.
That would be the easy way to say it. Okay, or it
could mean but if the case were to be against the woman,
so the woman could turn into a דיני נפשות dinei nefashot case,
we're always going to remain 23. But basically what this is doing
is this is doing exactly what we saw in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi,
except now that we saw the ירושלמי Yerushalmi it reads a lot
better. We started by saying the case was against the woman, that's
one way of framing the debate. Now we're saying oh, but if
it was the case against the man, the חכמים Chachamim who say
when the case is against the woman it's always 23 because the
woman herself could be put to death if it turned into a
דיני נפשות dinei nefashot case, that's מקום נפשות mekom nefashot 23, there
they're going to say you always start with 23. But when the
case is against the man, he, even though the witnesses are going
to get put to death, he's always never going to be more
than three. So that's what they're saying. If it's against the man,
we'll say three. Okay, but if it's against the woman and it
could turn into a דיני נפשות dinei nefashot case, that'll be 23.
So it's just like the ירושלמי Yerushalmi switched from those two cases,
two different ways of understanding which one would more demand starting with
23. You could say the woman more demands 23, which is what
we're saying now, because she could always turn into דיני נפשות. dinei
nefashot. The man will never be דיני נפשות, dinei nefashot, he's always
three. Or you could say the reverse. In the man's case, there's
always somebody getting put to death, so everybody's going to need 23.
The issue of זוממין zomemin would be resolved in the same trial,
or they wouldn't have a separate trial?
Yeah, so that's seems to be to some degree what we're discussing.
You know, the general sense you get is that it's the same
trial. And here though the question is, so you might split it
off though, because here oh, זוממין, zomemin, you go to your בית
דין beit din of 23, and the man now you're going to
just deal with him as a separate type of a case. You
know, but it would be the same trial that they were in
the process of trying to get her put to death. It's just
the same. Yeah, exactly. Okay. Yes?
If she's not a virgin, she doesn't get death, right? It's only
if she did adultery after she's married.
Correct, after קידושין. kiddushin. There's two stages, remember, there's קידושין kiddushin and
נישואין. nisuin. On the wedding night, after they are finally having sex,
he finds out she's not a virgin, but she's been married to
him for the last year, let's say. So the question is, had,
did she have that act of sex in the last year,
in the... Yeah, that's different.
That's not adultery, right? That's just...
well, he suspects adultery.
No, I mean, that's not a death sentence, it's just according to
the ritual and if she dies, she dies, right?
Right, right. But if witnesses come and prove she committed adultery, she
would get death. Even then? Sure, that's just a case of adultery
in any case. Yeah, okay, yeah.
So it's obvious that the אבי הנערה, avi hana'arah, her father, right?
Yeah, yeah. But of course she is here a non-subject to the
proceeding. She's the... like she's the... it's all between the men here
is the way it's sort of framed in the Torah.
It doesn't mean she's not a woman in it.
All right. So anyway, so it says okay, okay. אביי אמר, Abaye
amar, so anyway, so now we've got two reads of that, right,
whether the חכמים Chachamim would switch their position or would agree that
you can start with three when it's about the man, not about
the woman. But now we've had two reads, רבה Raba and עולא,
Ulla, that it was against the woman. Okay. And the question is,
do we start with three or do we start with twenty-three when
it's against the woman? And against the man might be a different
story. Now, now you could just stop here. We've laid out the
basic approaches to this debate. This is where the ירושלמי Yerushalmi stops.
But here's also where you see that the בבלי, Bavli, you know,
sort of, you know, a type of a normal mode of the
בבלי, Bavli, which is you have a cryptic debate, you have a
debate in the משנה, Mishnah, it's not clear what. Let's use this
as an opportunity to suggest a million possibilities about what they might
be debating about and drawing on other types of debates that we're
aware of. Okay. So what now we're going to see is what
I would call wild reads of the משנה, Mishnah, which are completely
absent from the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, but because it's not clear what חכמים
Chachamim and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir are debating, it allows us to
read into it other types of debates. So let's take a look.
And it's clear it's the later אמוראים Amoraim who are suggesting this.
אביי אמר דכולי עלמא חיישינן ללעז, Abaye amar dechulei alma chaishinan l'la'az,
everybody might agree we're concerned about לעז la'az that three will turn
into
twenty-three, ומשום כבודן של ראשונים, umishum kvodan shel rishonim, and this issue
about, you know, if a בית דין Beit Din disperses, is it
going to be respectful for the original judges? Forget those issues. הכא
במאי עסקינן, Hacha b'mai askinan, what are we talking about? כגון דאתרו
בה סתם, k'gon de'atru bah stam, it's a case against her, like
we've been assuming,
and but they gave her התראה hatra'ah and they didn't tell her
what type of death penalty she would be deserving. They just said
if you commit adultery you're חייב מיתה. chayav mitah. They didn't tell
her which מיתה. mitah. דהאי תנא הוא דתניא, D'hai tanna hu detanya,
and it's this תנא tanna that we taught: ושאר כל חייבי מיתות
שבתורה, v'shear kol chayavei mitot shebaTorah, all other, meaning the discussion there
in a תוספתא Tosefta was about the מסית ומדיח, meisit umadiach, the
person who seduces to idolatry, and there you hide the witnesses, you
only give a very subtle warning, you try to... so it's a
little bit of entrapment with that person, not totally, but anyway. But
it says that's by the מסית ומדיח, meisit umadiach, but ושאר כל
חייבי מיתות שבתורה, v'shear kol chayavei mitot shebaTorah, but all other death
penalties in the Torah, אין ממיתים אותם אלא בעדה, ein memitim otam
ela b'edah, it
requires a full community, meaning a בית דין Beit Din of twenty-three,
ועדים, v'edim, and witnesses that are not hidden but are obvious, והתראה,
v'hatra'ah, and explicit warning, עד שיודיעו שהוא חייב מיתה בבית דין. ad
sheyodi'u shehu chayav mitah b'veit din. And you have to know not
just it's forbidden to do it, but it's deserving of a death
in the court. It has to be התראה hatra'ah with a clear
sense of the punishment. רבי יהודה אומר עד שיודיעוהו באיזו מיתה הוא
נהרג. Rabbi Yehuda omer ad sheyodi'uhu b'eizo mitah hu neherag. It's not
enough to tell them that you're חייב מיתה, chayav mitah, it has
to be which one you're deserving of. So what does that mean?
So it means now רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says three cause רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says, oh, this'll never turn into a דיני נפשות
dinei nefashot case because the witnesses didn't tell her which specific, you
know, death penalty she would be... she would be... it would be
warranting. וחכמים V'chachamim say no, no, no, you have to start with
twenty-three because it is going to be a דיני נפשות dinei nefashot
case because even without being specific about the death penalty, you could
put... you know, the person could be חייב מיתה. chayav mitah. So
of course has nothing to do, right, with what it seems like
they're really debating. Let's just import some other debate. רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says they'll never be death penalty because they did the warning
incorrectly, וחכמים v'Chachamim say twenty-three because there can be a death penalty.
Now we're going to have another, another series of things like this.
Okay.
רב פפא אמר הכא באשה חברה עסקינן. Rav Pappa amar hacha b'ishah
chaverah askinan. We're talking about a woman who is a חברה, chaverah,
she's like from, you know, she's a learned woman.
וקמיפלגי בפלוגתא דרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה ורבנן. Ukmiplagi biplugta d'Rabbi Yosi be'Rabbi
Yehuda v'rabanan. And the case is they didn't give her warning, and
it's the following debate. דתניא רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר חבר אין
צריך התראה. Detanya Rabbi Yosi be'Rabbi Yehuda omer chaver ein tzarich hatra'ah.
If somebody is like a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and knows the
הלכה, halacha, then you don't have to give them warning, because the
whole purpose of warning is to know that the person is aware
of the gravity of their sin. And if somebody is knowledgeable and
clearly aware, it's sort of like saying like if somebody is a
criminal lawyer you don't have to warn them because they obviously know
what crime they're committing. Okay. לפי שלא ניתנה התראה אלא להבחין בין
שוגג למזיד. Lefi shelo nitna hatra'ah ela lehavchin bein shogeg l'mezid. The
whole purpose of התראה hatra'ah is to know if the person is
intentional or unintentional. intentional or unintentional, and therefore you don't need it.
And the answer and the other answer is, no, you always need
it. Why would you always need it? Well, for the one part,
how do you exactly identify whether somebody does know something or not
know something? People can forget in the moment of passion. But the
other explanation also is it's not just, the purpose of hatra'ah התראה
hatra'ah is not just to determine intentionality, the purpose of hatra'ah התראה
hatra'ah is to make the sin one of defiance. You know, if
you tell me I'm not allowed to do it and what my
punishment will be and I say af al pi chen אף על
פי כן, af al pi chen, I'm not just sinning, there's a
certain element of like rejecting and defying. The other way to explain
it even taking that one step further is the Gemara later in
Sanhedrin סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, we're going to see this coming up, says ad
sheyatir atzmo l'oso misa עד שיתיר עצמו לאותה מיתה. ad sheyatir atzmo
l'oso misa. That there's always this question about what gives the court
the right to use violence against another person and to take another
person's life? But if the person says I know I am going
to be chayav misa חייב מיתה chayav misa and I accept that
upon me in the performance of this sin, then you basically have
given the court license now to take your life. Okay? So it's
part of what allows them to execute somebody. So anyway, there's different
explanations of hatra'ah התראה hatra'ah which are not just to determine intentionality,
what the Gemara will get to it, I have to find the
daf, but later in Sanhedrin סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, I think nun נ nun
something, whatever, I'll find it. Anyway, okay. So anyway, so this,
that's the debate. Is the woman going to be chayav misa חייב
מיתה chayav misa or not? She didn't get hatra'ah התראה hatra'ah but
she was a talmidat chacham תלמידת חכם, talmidat chacham, so therefore or
chachama חכמה, chachama, anyway, and therefore, you know,
Rabbi Meir says she'll never get misa מיתה, misa, you didn't do
warning, three. And the Chachamim חכמים Chachamim say she gets misa מיתה,
misa, we don't need warning, twenty-three. Okay. Rav Ashi amar k'gon רב
אשי אמר כגון, Rav Ashi amar k'gon, we're going to have a
series of these, d'asru bah דאסהרו בה d'asru bah b'malkus v'lo asru
bah b'ketala במלקות ולא אסהרו בה בקטלא. b'malkus v'lo asru bah b'ketala.
They warned her with malkus מלקות, malkus, they said, hey, if you
commit adultery you'll get lashes. They gave her the wrong warning, not
death penalty. So she's never going to get the death penalty. Everybody
would agree if she said lashes and not death penalty, you can't
give the person the death penalty. Ah, so the question is she's
chayav malkus חייב מלקות. chayav malkus. But does malkus מלקות malkus get
three or twenty-three? Okay. V'kamifligi b'plugta d'Rabbi Yishmael v'Rabbanan וכמיפלגי בפלוגתא דרבי
ישמעאל ורבנן, v'kamifligi b'plugta d'Rabbi Yishmael v'Rabbanan, the debate is the debate
we have later in our Mishnah משנה. Mishnah. D'nan: Malkus b'shlosha mishum
Rabbi Yishmael amru b'esrim u'shelosha דתנן מלקות בשלושה משום רבי ישמעאל אמרו
בעשרים ושלושה. d'nan malkus b'shlosha mishum Rabbi Yishmael amru b'esrim u'shelosha. Okay,
so that's a way of explaining the debate. It's only a case
of malkus מלקות, malkus, so does that get three or twenty-three? It
doesn't fit the language of the Mishnah משנה Mishnah at all, because
the Mishnah משנה Mishnah said the Chachamim חכמים Chachamim say you get
twenty-three because there's dinei nefashot דיני נפשות. dinei nefashot. According to this,
it has nothing to do with dinei nefashot דיני נפשות, dinei nefashot,
you get twenty-three because malkus מלקות malkus is twenty-three. Anyway, I don't
understand why they didn't just say that therefore they're debating the case
of the man. The man does get malkus מלקות, malkus, he pays
a hundred shekel and gets malkus מלקות. malkus. So according to this,
just say they're debating the man, not the woman. So Rabbi Meir
says three because malkus מלקות malkus is three and the Chachamim חכמים
Chachamim say twenty-three. This is a very weak read. Anyway, moving on.
Ravina amar k'gon רבינא אמר כגון Ravina amar k'gon she'nimtza echad min
ha'edim karov u'pasul שנמצא אחד מן העדים קרוב ופסול. she'nimtza echad min
ha'edim karov u'pasul. Oh, here's the issue. Can, is she going to
be chayav misa חייב מיתה chayav misa and twenty-three or not and
get three? And what's the issue? You had three witnesses that say
she committed adultery and one of them is a relative. So does
that mean that you can still have the other two find her
guilty? And Rabbi Meir says no, she's never going to be, it's
not found guilty with this. Everybody gets thrown out. It's only going
to be a monetary issue, three. And the Chachamim חכמים Chachamim say
we could kill, find her guilty, still find her guilty for committing
adultery and twenty-three. So what's this issue about karov u'pasul קרוב ופסול?
karov u'pasul? V'kamifligi b'plugta d'Rabbi Yosi v'Rebbe וכמיפלגי בפלוגתא דרבי יוסי ורבי,
v'kamifligi b'plugta d'Rabbi Yosi v'Rebbe, the debate of Rabbi Yosi and Rebbe
aliba d'Rabbi Akiva אליבא דרבי עקיבא, aliba d'Rabbi Akiva, who debate within
Rabbi Akiva's position. What does this mean? D'nan דתנן, d'nan, Rabbi Akiva
omer: Lo bashlishi ela l'hachmir alav l'asot dino k'yotze b'elu רבי עקיבא
אומר לא בשלישי אלא להחמיר עליו לעשות דינו כיוצא באלו. Rabbi Akiva
omer lo bashlishi ela l'hachmir alav l'asot dino k'yotze b'elu. He says
when the Torah תורה Torah says al pi shnayim edim o shlosha
edim yumat hamet על פי שנים עדים או שלשה עדים יומת המת.
al pi shnayim edim o shlosha edim yumat hamet. Why does it
have to say three people? If it says you get, two witnesses
can get you killed, three can also get you killed. So Rabbi
Akiva says it is coming to be strict on the third guy
and to say, let's say you had three witnesses that found Reuven,
Shimon, and Levi ראובן שמעון ולוי Reuven Shimon v'Levi and they're test,
they're not brothers they testified in that order, and then they were
all proven to be zomemin זוממין. zomemin. And
so are you going to kill Levi לוי? Levi? Because Levi לוי
Levi could say, you know what, even if I didn't show up
to court, Reuven ראובן Reuven and Shimon שמעון Shimon already were going
to get the person chayav misa חייב מיתה, chayav misa, my testimony
didn't add anything. So since my testimony didn't make this person more
chayav misa חייב מיתה, chayav misa, I should not get the punishment
of edim zomemin עדים זוממין, edim zomemin, right? What I did was
not consequential. So Rabbi Akiva says that's why it says two or
three. That the third one is going to get the same punishment
as the first two, even though he came third and it wasn't
really necessary. And the litigant brought a third, no, you only need
two witnesses to make them zomemin זוממין. zomemin. No, if you brought
a third in order to strengthen the case, presumably, yeah. Lo bashlishi
ela l'hachmir alav l'asot dino k'yotze b'elu לא בשלישי אלא להחמיר עליו
לעשות דינו כיוצא באלו. lo bashlishi ela l'hachmir alav l'asot dino k'yotze
b'elu. That he has the same punishment as the first two if
they're zomemin זוממין. zomemin. Im ken unash shekatav hakatuv l'nitpal l'ovrei aveira
k'ovrei aveira אם כן עונש שכתב הכתוב לנטפל לעוברי עבירה כעוברי עבירה,
im ken unash shekatav hakatuv l'nitpal l'ovrei aveira k'ovrei aveira, and the
Torah תורה Torah therefore punished the nitpal overei aveira k'overei aveira לנטפל
לעוברי עבירה כעוברי עבירה l'nitpal l'ovrei aveira k'ovrei aveira and as the
לעוברי עבירה כעוברי עבירה. l'nitpal l'ovrei aveira k'ovrei aveira. one who sort
of what's a good word for נטפל nitepal one who sort of
appends himself you know is a tagalong to the sinner for real
right but he tagged on to them somebody who's tagging himself on
peripheral in a peripheral way to the sinners and he's treated like
the principal sinners themselves okay so עד כמה וכמה שישלם שכר הנטפל
לעושה מצוה כעושה מצוה ad kamma v'kamma she-yishalem schar ha-nitpal l'oseh mitzvah
k'oseh mitzvah so how much more so if you have a group
of people I don't know they're all going on שבת Shabbos to
do ביקור חולים bikur cholim and somebody says oh I'll tag along
okay so you know what we had 20 people without you like
you're not really adding too much okay but nevertheless you're going to
get the same reward as the prince as the principal actors okay
that was a nice little דרש drash but anyway but now we're
getting to our point here's another reason two and three are linked
ומה שנים u'ma shnayim the same way if you have only two
witnesses נמצא אחד מהם קרוב או פסול עדותן בטלה nimtza echad meihem
karov o pasul eidusam bateila if one of them is invalid everything
gets thrown out because then you're only left with one אף שלשה
נמצא אחד מהם קרוב או פסול עדותן בטלה af shlosha nimtza echad
meihem karov o pasul eidusam bateila if three one of them is
invalid they all get thrown out ומניין שאפילו מאה u'minayin she-afillu me'ah
how do I know if you have a hundred and one of
them is invalid they all get thrown out תלמוד לומר עדים talmud
lomar eidim
witnesses they're all treated as one unit now that we know the
principal law of נמצא אחד מהם קרוב או פסול
nimtza echad meihem karov
o pasul but so what's the debate everybody should say all the
witnesses get thrown out but the debate is what is the scope
of what רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva said is it always true or
does it require some other parameters and here we have a debate
אמר רבי יוסי amar rabbi yose says רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose במה
דברים אמורים b'me devarim amurim when is it true that you throw
them all out בדיני נפשות b'dinei nefashos if it's a capital crime
אבל בדיני ממונות תתקיים עדות בשאר aval b'dinei mamonos tiskayem eidus bishar
but if it's a monetary crime then just keep the kosher witnesses
they're not all treated as one big unit and keep the kosher
ones and those will still be valid even if some of them
are
invalid that's רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose רבי אומר rebbi omer רבי Rebbi
says a different distinction אחד דיני ממונות ואחד דיני נפשות echad dinei
mamonos v'echad dinei nefashos
even by בדיני ממונות dinei mamonos if one is invalid you'll throw
them all out however in which case ואימתי v'eimatai when is it
true בזמן שהתרו בהן b'zman she-histru bahem
if the other witnesses showed their active participation by giving התראה hatra'ah
warning okay now of course the question is how is התראה hatra'ah
relevant by בדיני ממונות dinei mamonos תוספות tosfos tries to figure that
in but you could have by בדיני ממונות dinei mamonos everybody as
a unit or and בדיני נפשות dinei nefashos but there's ways even
in בדיני נפשות dinei nefashos that extra people won't be considered part
of the witnesses if it wasn't obvious that they were there to
testify one of the ways to make it obvious that you're there
to testify is that you actively warn the person at least in
a בדיני נפשות dinei nefashos case okay אבל בזמן שלא התרו בהן
aval b'zman she-lo histru bahem but if there wasn't warning so מה
יעשו שני אחים באחד שראו באחד שהרג את הנפש mah ya'asu shenei
achim b'echad she-ra'u b'echad she-harag es ha-nefesh
so what happened you have ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon brothers going
down the street with מרדכי Mordechai and they see a murder committed
so all of a sudden you can't go ahead and just take
the two kosher witnesses they say oh נמצא אחד מהם קרוב או
פסול nimtza echad meihem karov o pasul so רבי Rebbi makes a
very logical point נמצא אחד מהם קרוב או פסול nimtza echad meihem
karov o pasul is not going to happen unless there's something that
identifies everybody as a witness just passive seeing of it would not
make you into a witness okay so one way is to say
it only applies to בדיני נפשות dinei nefashos רבי Rebbi is saying
it applies to both but only if you're somehow actively a witness
now this leads
to תוספות tosfos asking the raising the important question about how come
every wedding isn't פסול pasul because there's always relatives in the audience
okay so I just have to read you one line of this
very large תוספות tosfos on ט עמוד א tes amud aleph if
you take a look
that's why you do
יחוד עדים yichud eidim but according but that's not in the גמרא
gemara anyway and according to a number of פוסקים poskim יחוד עדים
yichud eidim doesn't help doesn't do anything okay so look at this
תוספות tosfos בזמן שהתרו בהן b'zman she-histru bahem
תוספות tosfos says this on ט עמוד א tes amud aleph מפרש
פרק קמא דמכות הכי אמרינן להו לאסהודי אתיתון meforash perek kama de-makkos
hachi amrinan lehu le-asudei asisun did you come to testify או למיחזי
אתיתון o le-michei asisun or you just coming to watch okay אם
אמרו לאסהודי אתינא נמצא אחד מהם קרוב או פסול עדותן בטלה im
amru le-asudei asina nimtza echad meihem karov o pasul eidusam bateila if
they say we're coming to testify so it's not testifying giving warning
there's other ways to make yourself an active witness okay then you
invalidate all the rest ואי אמרו למיחזי אתינא ve-i amru le-michei asina
no we're just coming to watch so in that case מה יעשו
שני אחים mah ya'asu shenei achim okay ונראה לרי ve-nireh la-ri now
it seems to רי Ri דמשום שנתכוונו להעיד de-mishum she-niskanu le-ha'id just
because they
even that's not enough just intending to bear witness לא אמרינן נמצא
אחד מהם קרוב או פסול עדותן בטלה lo amrinan nimtza echad meihem
karov o pasul eidusam bateila that would not be enough to invalidate
everybody why אלא שהולכין ומעידין כולם בבית דין ella she-holchin u-mei'idin kulin
b'beis din
you need them not just to witness it the event with intent
to serve as a witness you need them to show up to
בית דין beis din with the intent to be a witness okay
אבל משום ראייה לחוד שנתכוונו להעיד לא aval mishum re'iyah lachud she-niskanu
le-ha'id lo
but just seeing something even if you're doing it with the intent
to be a witness is not enough to invalidate דאי לא תימא
הכי כל גיטין כשנותנין אותן בפני קרובים ופסולים יפסלו אם נתכוין האחד
de-i lo teima hachi kol gittin keshe-nosnin osan bifnei krovim u-psulin yipsalu
im niskan ha-echad
okay any גיטין gittin that there's relatives there if they're intending to
be a witness they should invalidate and he doesn't oh he doesn't
mention the witness the wedding. just the גיטין. gittin. But anyway, then
he goes on, so this becomes this big issue of what do
you need to label yourself as a witness. רבי Rebbi says warning,
but warning only works in capital crimes, it doesn't work in דיני
ממונות, dinei mamonot, it doesn't work in קידושין, kiddushin, it doesn't work
in גיטין. gittin. I mean, I guess you can make a joke
about a warning in קידושין, kiddushin, people need התראה. hatra'ah. Okay, hey,
look what you're getting into, but anyway. Okay, but anyway, but so
maybe you need intent, but is it enough to intend to see
at the time or do you have to show up to בית
דין? Beis Din? Like how exactly do you get labeled as a
witness, so נמצא אחד קרוב או פסול nimtza echad karov o pasul
would be relevant? So that's a very big question in the ראשונים.
Rishonim. But anyway, let's say how does this fit in our משנה?
mishna? The way it fits in our משנה mishna is the following.
There was three witnesses,
okay, so one of them was פסול. pasul. So רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir says, oh, so therefore it's דיני ממונות dinei mamonot because like
the רבי יוסי's Rebbi Yosi position, you can still use the two
כשר kasher ones for דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, so you'll have a
case of three. It's a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot against the woman,
but she's never going to be חייב מיתה chayav misa
because they, you know, it invalidates all of them to serve in
a capital crime. What would the חכמים Chachamim hold who say twenty-three?
They would hold like רבי, Rebbi, they would say that invalid witness
did not invalidate the group for דיני נפשות dinei nefashot because the
invalid witness didn't warn. And since the invalid witness didn't warn or
didn't intend to be a witness, then the remaining two can still
serve as דיני נפשות. dinei nefashot. Okay, so now we've got the
debate to be one of them was invalid. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
says it's only a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot case, you're allowed to
keep the two good ones for דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, but it's
not a דיני נפשות. dinei nefashot. And חכמים Chachamim say it's a
דיני נפשות dinei nefashot because you can throw out the one witness
who didn't do the warning and wasn't an active witness, and you
can throw that one out and still retain the two for דיני
נפשות. dinei nefashot.
Rabbi, but in that case, the one that didn't give the warning
that gets thrown out and then you keep two valid witnesses, that
one has to be one of the two קרובים krovim to each
other.
Yeah, yeah, it's the one that invalidates and you're left with two
good ones.
Correct. And so it's one of those two אחים, achim, I guess?
Correct. Correct. Okay. ואי בעית אימא, V'ee bayis eima, if you want
you could say, so here's another yet another way of explaining the
debate of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and the חכמים. Chachamim. All of
these are of course totally not פשט. peshat. Okay, the פשט peshat
were the ones we had at the beginning which are paralleling what
we had in the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. ואי בעית אימא, V'ee bayis eima,
if you want you could
say שהשיאו באחרים ולא השיאו בעדים. she'hisiyu b'acherim v'lo hisiyu b'edim. Here's
the issue, can it be a דיני נפשות dinei nefashot case that
you had other people who weren't the witnesses who gave the warning,
hey don't commit adultery you'll be חייב מיתה. chayav misa. ובמפלגי בפלוגתא
דרבי יוסי ורבנן, U'v'mapalgi b'plugta d'Rebbi Yosi v'Rabbanan,
it's a debate of רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi and רבנן. Rabbanan. דתנן,
Detnan, רבי יוסי אומר לעולם אינו נהרג עד שיהיו פי שנים עדים
מתרין בו. Rebbi Yosi omer l'olam eino neherag ad she'yiyu pi shnayim
edim matrin bo.
You need the witnesses themselves to deliver the warning. שנאמר Shene'emar על
פי שנים עדים, al pi shnayim edim, by the mouth of them.
So that's a debate. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says the warning was
done incorrectly, only ממונות mamonot three, and the חכמים Chachamim say the
warning was fine, it could be נפשות nefashot twenty-three. ואי בעית אימא,
V'ee bayis eima, if you want you could say דאכחשו בבדיקות ולא
אכחשו בחקירות, d'itchachashu b'bedikos v'lo itchachashu b'chakiyros,
that the witnesses who were coming to make this woman חייב מיתה
chayav misa committing adultery, they were shown to be they contradicted one
another
in the בדיקות, bedikos, which means like in the details of exactly
what happened, but not in the חקירות. chakiyros. The חקירות chakiyros is
when it happened. The when it happened, when and where it happened
is seen as central, and if you get any of those because
that's what can turn you into an עד זומם, ed zomem, because
we could say you couldn't have seen it at that time and
that place because you were with us. So if there's any contradiction
in the where and the when, the testimony is thrown out. But
what if the contradiction is in the what, you know, and some
minor detail of the what? Is that enough to throw them out?
Okay, so let's take a look. ובמפלגי בפלוגתא דבן זכאי ורבנן, U'v'mapalgi
b'plugta d'Ben Zakai v'Rabbanan, the debate of בן זכאי Ben Zakai and
the רבנן. Rabbanan. דתנן Detnan מעשה ובדק בן זכאי בעוקצי תאנים. Ma'aseh
u'vadak Ben Zakai b'uktzei te'einim. בן זכאי Ben Zakai would ask them,
so you say the crime happened under a fig tree, tell me,
you know, were the stems of the figs, were they pointed north
or were they pointed south, were they sharp or were they smooth?
And he would ask all these נודניק nudnik questions until he could
get them to trip up, you know, because the idea you try
to avoid דיני נפשות. dinei nefashot. So the point is, is that
enough to throw them out? So בן זכאי Ben Zakai says yes,
the חכמים Chachamim say no. So that's what happened. So רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir would say, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says yes you throw
them out, they're not good for דיני נפשות, dinei nefashot, it's only
a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot case, and the חכמים Chachamim say no,
even though they contradicted in those small points, they're still legitimate witnesses
and it's a דיני נפשות dinei nefashot case. Okay, so that was
about ten different reads of the משנה, mishna, of which eight of
them were really totally imported from elsewhere. Okay, but the real debates
are how much are we either concerned that the case against the
woman starts with דיני ממונות dinei mamonot will evolve to דיני נפשות,
dinei nefashot, so therefore should we start it with three or start
with twenty-three, or the other way of looking at it, you know,
is against the husband, against him it's a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot
but against his witnesses it's a דיני נפשות, dinei nefashot, and therefore
how much does that mean we're going to do a case of
three?
But what would you say, what do you think about this though
from the point of view of developing legal theory? So the פשט
pshat or not פשט pshat framework is limiting, the בבלי Bavli's agenda,
perhaps, takes this as an opportunity to—that is completely true.
The בבלי Bavli is much more interested in exploring ideas than in
always getting פשט pshat of a text, 100%. Let's just read one
more section here. Okay, אמר רב יוסף: amar Rav Yosef: הביא הבעל
עדים שזינתה heivi habaal eidim shezinta והביא האב עדים והזימום לעדי הבעל,
veheivi haav eidim vehizimum le'idei habaal, classic case of מוציא שם רע.
motzi shem ra. He brought witnesses she committed adultery, the father brought
witnesses that his witnesses were lying, were זוממים. zomemim. So now his
witnesses are חייב מיתה. chayav misa. So the point is,
והזימום לעדי הבעל, vehizimum le'idei habaal, עדי הבעל נהרגין. edei habaal neheragin.
So the husband's witnesses are put to death, they were trying to
kill her. ואין משלמין ממון, ve'ein meshalmin mammon, even though their testimony
would have also made her lose her כתובה, kesubah, they don't do
both of them. רש"י Rashi sort of says it's like a קים
ליה. kim lei. Okay, you punish them, they're חייב מיתה chayav misa
for trying to get her killed, okay, but even though they would
have also made her lose her כתובה, kesubah, they don't also have
to pay, they don't also pay the כתובה. kesubah. חזר והביא הבעל
עדים והזימום לעדי האב. chazar veheivi habaal eidim vehizimum le'idei haav. Now
let's say it's turned around yet again, okay, so now the husband
brought witnesses that the father's witnesses that made his first group זוממים
zomemim were the liars. So do you sort of get this? So
now it's the husband's witness, so it's now it's the father's witnesses
who were lying and trying to get the true witnesses killed. עדי
אב נהרגין, edei av neheragin, the father's witnesses are killed because they
were trying to get the husband's legitimate witnesses falsely accused and killed.
ומשלמין
ממון. umeshalmin mammon. They also pay money. Who do they pay money
to? The husband. Because when the father brought witnesses, what was the
consequences of the father's witnesses? That the husband's witnesses would get killed
and that the husband would pay a hundred שקל. shekel. That's your
classic מוציא שם רע. motzi shem ra. Okay, so now that those
were lying, they now get put to death because they were trying
to kill the witnesses and they pay, hopefully before they die, the
husband a hundred שקל. shekel. Okay, and we don't say it's קים
ליה kim lei because of what? Because ממון לזה ונפשות לזה. mammon
lezeh unefashot lezeh. We separate the court cases, like similar to discussions
before of separating a case of three and a case of 23.
So the crime against the witnesses, they were עדים זוממים eidim zomemim
and they have to pay and they have to get put to
death. The crime against the husband, they were עדים זוממים eidim zomemim
and they pay a hundred שקל. shekel. And those are two separate
crimes even though done in the same act and therefore it is
not a case of קים ליה. kim lei. Each one is adjudicated
separately and they both will have to owe the husband, they or
their estate, and they will also be put to death.
So now you've got this double עדים. eidim.